Federico Cipriani

federico.cipriani at linux.com · GitHub · LinkedIn

View This Resume on My Website

Summary

Lifelong, passionate programmer with 4 years as a full-stack developer and almost 4 years as a DevOps/SRE and FinOps. I am a hardcore Linux user with nearly a decade of experience in Arch Linux and several years as a dedicated NixOS user.

Education

Electronic Technician

Otto Krause · Buenos Aires, Argentina

Space Systems Engineering

Universidad Nacional de San Martín (UNSAM) · Buenos Aires, Argentina

Languages

I am an EU citizen (Italian) with native proficiency in Spanish and C2 proficiency in English.

Experience

Site Reliability Engineer

Yuno · Hybrid: Buenos Aires, Argentina & Bogotá, Colombia

06/2022 - 11/2024

- Terraforming multiple AWS accounts, with network peering for multiple purposes.
- Provisioning and maintaining several EKS clusters, alongside managing their service mesh.
- Adopted Datadog, providing instrumentation while controlling data ingestion and costs.
- Proactively met weekly to analyze cloud spending and plan FinOps automation strategies.
- Engaged with cloud provider teams to assess technical and cost-fit solutions for our needs.
- Designed dashboards and monitors for SLOs, collaborating on SLI definitions with various teams.
- Implemented near real-time Change Data Capture (CDC) pipelines for the Data team's BI needs.
- Co-led Reliability Track sessions, using Testkube to stress test and boost core product performance.
- Developed integrations for tools such as Argo ecosystem, AWS, Datadog, Kubernetes, Opsgenie, and Slack.

Site Reliability Engineer

Agot AI · Hybrid: Buenos Aires, Argentina & Pittsburgh, US

03/2021 - 05/2022

- Provisioning a hybrid on-premise cloud with K3S on Nvidia Jetson.
- Review and refactoring of technology stacks in both FrontEnd and BackEnd areas.
- Quality control and code sanitization of all projects through GitLab CI pipeline jobs (ShellCheck, Pytest, etc).
- Research and benchmarking of cloud-based Machine Learning training tools (SageMaker, MLFlow, and Kubeflow).
- Inference box servers budget & compatibility planning for on-premise instances.

Software Engineer

Democracia en Red (DeR) · Remote: Buenos Aires, Argentina

11/2020 - 04/2021

- Development of full-stack solutions with Svelte and FastAPI technologies for a civic software platform.
- Integration with Blockchain Federal Argentina (BFA) Proof of Authority (PoA) network for an e-voting system.
- Prototyping, implementation, and maintenance of standardized solutions.

Software Engineer

Nevrona · Remote: Buenos Aires, Argentina

04/2019 - 12/2020

- Served as Lead Developer and Architect for the FrontEnd & Middleware team.
- Co-led development of a comprehensive work and social networking platform from inception.
- Designed and built administrative interface (backoffice) for platform management.
- Authored technical documentation and established FrontEnd and general development guidelines.
- Conducted technical interviews and recruitment for both BackEnd and FrontEnd teams.

System Administrator & SWE

APLI · On-site: Buenos Aires, Argentina

05/2017 - 12/2019

- Remote and on-site support of server infrastructure.
- Development of scripts and utilities for the shell in Bash, Perl, and Python.
- Monitoring and alarm systems with Nagios, Icinga, Nagstamon, and Prometheus.
- I've built a Raspberry-based monitor wall for a Network Operation Center (NOC).

Licenses & Certifications

I currently hold the following certified exams and courses:

- HashiCorp Certified: Terraform Associate (003).
- Linux Foundation: Ethics for Open Source Development (LFC104).
- Linux Foundation: Developing Secure Software (LFD121).
- Linux Foundation: Security Self-Assessments for Open Source Projects (LFEL1005).
- Linux Foundation: Securing Projects with OpenSSF Scorecard (LFEL1006).
- Linux Foundation: Automating Supply Chain Security SBOMs and Signatures (LFEL1007).
- Linux Foundation: Scaling Cloud Native Applications with KEDA (LFEL1014).
- Linux Foundation: XSS Exploits and Defenses (LFEL1010).

Skills & Tools

Cloud & Infrastructure

Ansible, Argo, AWS Ecosystem (ACM, CE, CloudWatch, CodeArtifact, EC2, ECR, ElastiCache, EKS, IAM, KMS, Lambda, RDS, Route53, S3, Secrets Manager, SQS, VPC), CI/CD, Infrastructure as Code (IaC), Istio, GitOps, Github Actions, Helm, Kustomize, Kubernetes, K3S, KEDA, NixOS, Service Mesh, Terraform, Terragrunt, Testkube, Velero.

Monitoring and Reliability

Alertmanager, Business Continuity Plan (BCP), Chaos Mesh, Datadog, Fluentd, Grafana, Prometheus, Obersvability Instrumentation, Incident Response Management, Opsgenie, Post Mortem Writing, Chaos Engineering, RPO/RTO, Stress Testing.

Security and Compliance

AIDE, Compliance, Encryption, FinOps, GDPR, LUKS, NIST Compliance, Nmap, OWASP, SAST, SBOMs, STRIDE model, Security Self-Assessment, WAF, Zero Trust Architecture.

Data Engineering

Airbyte, CDC, DVC, DynamoDB, ElasticSearch, ELT/ETL, Kafka, Kubeflow, MLOps, MSK, MySQL, MWAA, PeerDB, PostgreSQL, SageMaker.

Programming & Frameworks

ACID, Axum, CLEAN, CQRS, Deno, Express/Polka, FastAPI, Haskell, Nix/Flakes, NodeJS, Python, Rust, Shell, Svelte/Kit, Typer, Typescript.

Work Culture & Practices

Agile, Architecture Design Records (ADRs), Follow-The-Sun (GDSE), KPI/OKR Alignment, Async communication, Meeting Minutes & Outcome-Based Agendas.